The Robert S. Gottlieb recordings of North Indian tabla
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
The Robert S. Gottlieb recordings of North Indian tabla 1956-1972
AFC 2000/014
Gottlieb, Robert S.
approximately 94 items
1 container
1 linear inch
10 sound tape reels: analog; 5 in.
11 sound cassettes: analog
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Ethnographic field recordings of tabla drumming in North India and interviews with tabla musicians.
Provenance
Robert S. Gottlieb, donation, 2000.
Accruals
No further accruals expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Robert S. Gottlieb recordings of North Indian tabla are open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Notes
Robert S. Gottlieb was an ethnomusicologist and professor of music at the University of California, Riverside and Evergreen State College. In addition to his work on tabla music in North India, he also studied the music of Sudan and Kathak dance music in South India.
Scope and Content
The collection includes sound recordings of tabla performances by master performers in North India. Also included are sound recordings of interviews, and some associated transcripts, with master performers and their disciples. Interviews were conducted in Hindi with transcripts translating the interviews into English. Some of the tabla performance recordings were used in Gottlieb's publications: The Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming, 1977 and Solo Tabla Drumming of North India, 1993 and 1998. See Related Publications for a fuller citation of these works.
Arrangement
The Robert S. Gottlieb recordings of North Indian tabla are organized in two series:
Series 1: Tabla performances
Series 2: Interviews
The archivist arranged and described the sound recordings based on labels on the sound recordings and their carriers, not by listening to the recordings. As a result, errors and discrepancies may exist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alla Rakha; Gottlieb, Robert S.; Khan, Amir, Ustad; Khan, Habibuddin; Khan, Karamatullah, 1917-1977; Khan, Masit; Khan, Wājid Hussain; Khān, Inām Alī; Khān, Latif Āhmed, 1942-1989; Kishan Maharaj; Mahārāj, Kanțhé; Shejwal, Arjun; Thirakwa, Ahmedjan, Ustad, 1891-1979
Organizations
Sangeet Natak Akademi.
Subjects
Tabla music--India.; Tabla music--Instruction and study.; Tabla players--India--Interviews.; Tabla players--India.; Tabla--India.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Sound recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Tabla performances
  - Habibuddin Khan, AFC 2000/014: SR16; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - Side A: Solo tabla, January 1957, Recorded in Calcutta by Jnan Ghosh.
    - Side B: Solo tabla, March 1956, Recorded in New Delhi by Sangit Natak Akademi. Tape 1/31.
  - Sangit Natak Akademi tapes of Kanthe Maharaj, September 24, 1964, AFC 2000/014: SR10; Recorded in Calcutta. Copied by Robert S. Gottlieb with permission of the Sangit Natak Akademi, New Delhi.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
    - Red leader: #1/267 tintal and #1/268 brahmatal
    - Green leader: #1/270 Pancham Sawari Tal and #1/272 Ganesh Tal
  - Sangit Natak Akademi tapes of Keramatullah, circa 1965, AFC 2000/014: SR08; Recorded in New Delhi. Copied by Robert S. Gottlieb with permission of the Sangit Natak Akademi, New Delhi.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
    - Green leader: Performing tabla compositions of Masit Khan. Jhaptal, Ara-Chautal, Rupak., #1118
    - Red leader: Solo tabla - tintal, #1117. Keramatullah then renders the bols for specific compositions which follow.
  - Sangit Natak Akademi tape of Ahmadjan Thirakwa, August 3, 1966, AFC 2000/014: SR09; Copied by Robert S. Gottlieb with permission of the Sangit Natak Akademi, New Delhi.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
    - Green leader: Solo tabla in tintal, #1/298
    - Red leader: Interview with Brahaspati, #1/298
  - Keramatullah Khan - Tabla Lahara (tintal) accompanied by Mahesh Prasad Misra - Sarangi, May 1968, AFC 2000/014: SR06; Recorded in Calcutta. This performance has not been published.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
  - Amir Hussain - solo tabla, November 17, 1968, AFC 2000/014: SR07; Recorded in Bombay by A.K. Thatte.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
  - Performances of Kishan Maharaj and Wazid Hussain, AFC 2000/014: SR03; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
    - Green leader: Performance of Kishan Maharaj, April 21, 1971, Recorded in Benares.
    - Red leader: Performance of Wazid Hussain, April 20, 1971, Recorded in Lucknow.
  - Wazid Hussain reciting bols for his performance, April 20, 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR15; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - Tabla performance of Keramatullah Khan, May 10, 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR02; Recorded in Calcutta. This performance used for publications: Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming, 1977 and Solo Tabla Drumming of North India, 1993 and 1998.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
  - Bols and performances, AFC 2000/014: SR19; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - Side A: Hashmat Ali bols for Habibuddin's 1956 and 1957 performances, July 24, 1971, See AFC 2000/014: SR16
    - Side B: Keramatullah alternate performance, May 10, 1971, Not published.
  - Tabla performances of Inam Ali Khan, AFC 2000/014: SR01; Recorded in Bombay.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
    - Green leader, October 5, 1971, This performance used for Anthology Record, 1975.
    - Red leader, October 6, 1971, This performance used for publications: Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming, 1977 and Solo Tabla Drumming of North India, 1993 and 1998.
  - Tabla performance of Alla Rakha, January 1972, AFC 2000/014: SR04; Recorded in Bombay. Selections from these performances were combined for use in Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming, 1977 and Solo Tabla Drumming of North India, 1993 and 1998.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
  - Bols and performances, AFC 2000/014: SR21; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - Side A: Bols for performance of Alla Rakha recited by Zakir Hussain, January 10, 1972, Recorded in Bombay. See AFC 2000/014: SR04
    - Side B: Recorded performance of Alla Rakha, January 1972, Recorded in Bombay. This was abridged for Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming, 1977 and Solo Tabla Drumming of North India, 1993 and 1998.
  - Edited tapes of Habibuddin and Alla Rakha, undated, AFC 2000/014: SR05; Ajrala compositions selected from older recordings. See AFC 2000/014: SR16. The edited performance of Alla Rakha which was published.; 1 sound tape reel: analog, 5 in.
  - Bols, undated, AFC 2000/014: SR20; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - Side A: Arvind Mulgaonkar bols for miscellaneous gharana compositions, Recorded in Bombay.
    - Side B: Arjun Shejwal pakhawaj player, bols for miscellaneous compositions and parkhans and their rendition on pakharaj
- Series 2: Interviews
  - Miscellaneous interviews, Calcutta, AFC 2000/014: SR13; 1 sound cassette: analog
    - Side A: Masit Khan playing tabla and reminiscing about his musical background, March 2, 1971, Interview in Hindi.
    - Side B: Interview with Jnan Ghosh, Keramatullah, and Masit Khan about rhythmic manipulations, February 9, 1971, Interview in Hindi.
  - [Interview synopsis - Jnan Ghosh], February 9, 1971, 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - [Interview transcript - Masit Khan and Keramatullah], March 2, 1971, 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Interview with Kishan Maharaj, Benares, April 21, 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR17; Five classes of lay, discussion with bols, bols for Tabla Lahara, five lay illustration (tukras), gharana style and terms, five lay repeated.; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - [Translation of interview - Kishan Maharaj], April 21, 1971, 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Interview with Wazid Hussain, Lucknow, April 21, 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR14; Gharana genealogy, gat (Abid Hussain), gat features, mixed parhan (tabla), pure tabla, chakradar (Wazid Hus), comp/(Farukhabad model), tukra, peshkar, miscellaneous elaborations.; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - [Interview transcript - Wazid Hussain], April 21, 1971, 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - Interview with Habibuddin, Meerut, July 24, 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR18; Interviewing Habibuddin who was paralyzed at the time. He could no longer perform and was barely able to speak. When asked about the compositions he performed for the 1956 and 1957 recordings, he responded by fingering the bols on the arm of his disciple Hashmat Ali who was then able to recite them.; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - Interview with Inam Ali, Bombay, September 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR11; Interview in Hindi.; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - Interview with Inam Ali and his disciple Latif Ahmed, Bombay, September 1971, AFC 2000/014: SR12; Interview in Hindi. Subjects include: bols of tabla and distinction pertaining to palta and bal.; 1 sound cassette: analog
  - [Manuscript materials accompanying sound recordings], 1 folder (Folder 5)
Related Publications
Gottlieb, Robert S. The Major Traditions of North Indian Tabla Drumming: A Survey Presentation Based on Performances by India's Leading Artists: Illustrated with Recordings and Transcriptions of the Performances. Munich: Musikverlag E. Katzbichler, 1977.
Gottlieb, Robert S. Solo Tabla Drumming of North India: Its Repertoire, Styles, and Performance Practices. 1st ed. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass Publishers, 1993.
Gottlieb, Robert S. Solo Tabla Drumming of North India: Its Repertoire, Styles, and Performance Practices. 2nd ed. Delhi, Motilal Banarsidass Publishers, 1998.
Khan, Inam Ali and Sultan Khan, performers and Robert Gottlieb, compiler. North Indian Tabla Drumming. Anthology, 1975.
Khan, Ustad Keramatullah, performer and Robert Gottlieb, compiler. 42 Lessons for Tabla: Illustrated with Examples and Recordings of Master Performer Ustad Keramatullah Khan. Folkways Records CRB 12, 1973.